Last Episode: Memories of the
Blue Planet
The ship sustained only minimal damage in the last fight.
It won't affect our return. There were seventeen dead.
Thirty-four wounded.
Damn it!
Operations Officer Mori was also shot, and is in a coma.
Any chance she'll recover?
Unfortunately,
a miracle would have to occur.
Miracles don't just happen.
You need to make them happen.
（相原）地球との回線
つながりました！
We have a channel open to Earth!
（一同）ん？
ピピッ（受信音）
This is Todo, at Yamato Plan HQ.
（藤堂・通信）こちら
ヤマト計画本部　藤堂だ。→
Yamato, do you read me?
ヤマト　聞こえるか？
（一同）おお～！
This is the Yamato. We have received the Cosmo Reverse System from Iscandar.
（真田）こちらヤマト。
イスカンダルにて→
コスモリバースシステムを受領。
現在　地球に向けて　帰投中です。
We're now returning to Earth.
（藤堂）おお…　そうか。→
I see. Then Iscandar was real!
イスカンダルは
幻ではなかったのだな。→
本当に…
本当に　よくやってくれた。
You did it... You really did it!
We've waited this past year, gritting our teeth,
（土方）この１年近くの間→
我々は待った。　歯を食いしばり→
ヤマトの帰還に
希望をつないで待ったのだ。
resting all our hopes on the Yamato's return.
（藤堂）ん？　艦長は？→
Where is the Captain? Where is Okita?
沖田君はいないのか？
（真田）艦長は→
His Planet Bomb Syndrome has returned, and he isn't in good shape.
遊星爆弾症候群を再発されて→
容体が思わしくありません。
（藤堂）そうか…。
（土方）真田君→
Very well... Sanada, is Yuki all right?
雪は　元気かね？
森船務長は　戦闘で負傷。　現在…。
Operations Officer Mori was wounded in combat. She's presently...
ザザーー（ノイズ）
（藤堂）ん？　どうした　ヤマト。→
What's wrong, Yamato? Do you read me? Yamato!
聞こえているか？　ヤマト！
The hyperspace relays are still unstable.
（相原）まだ
超空間リレーが不安定です。→
We're still working on them. Give me some time.
開発中のものなので時間を下さい。
（南部）
でも　帰って来たんだな　俺たち。
But we're back!
（太田）ああ。　帰って来た。
Yeah, we're back.
（古代進）おいおい
太陽圏が近くなったからって→
Hey... Just because we're near the Solar System, don't lower your guard.
気を緩めるなよ。
（南部）あっ　ああ…。
（太田）でも　これで→
But now we know our families back on Earth are safe.
地球で待ってる家族の安否も
分かりますね。
Did you hear that rumor about the ghost?
（柏木）聞いた？
例の　幽霊が出るってうわさ。
（新見）ん!?
（沢村）今度は防衛軍の制服だって？
I heard it's wearing a Defense Force uniform now.
What I saw turned out to be Yurisha.
（林）俺が見たのって
結局　ユリーシャだったんだよな。
（柏木）残念でした。
（新見）はっ！
Too bad... I heard it's a guy this time.
（柏木）今度は　男性らしいよ。
（沢村）ちぇ～！　男かぁ。
A guy?
And what's more, it isn't a uniform from this ship!
（柏木）それがさ
この艦の制服じゃないらしいんだ。
（林）
それじゃあ　ほかの艦ってこと？
Then, from another ship?
（沢村）なんで　ほかの艦の幽霊が→
Why would a ghost from another ship be on the Yamato?
ヤマトに出るんだよ。
はっ！
It's a mystery.
（柏木）ミステリーよね。
（林）だよな。
Yeah.
（柏木）
あっ　そういえば　森船務長…。
Come to think of it, Operations Officer Mori...
あぁ…。
（沢村）知ってる。　副長の発案で→
I know.
The XO suggested putting her in there.
あそこに入ってるんだろ？
（ハーモニカの演奏）
（佐渡・回想）
((地球に戻り　しかるべき施設に→
If we can return to Earth, and get her to a real hospital...
入れられれば…　いや→
No, even then, the probability of survival is under 0.1%...
それでも　助かる可能性は→
０．１％にも満たんじゃろう))
((でも…
でも　可能性はあるんですよね？))
But...
But it's still possible, right?
（佐渡）
((じゃが　おそらく　彼女の体は→
I don't think her body will last that long.
それまで　もたん))
((んん…))
（佐渡）((そこでじゃ))
((あっ))
And so...
There's a way we can at least stabilize things.
（真田）((現状を維持するだけなら
方法はある))
((あっ))
（真田）((昏睡状態だった→
We can use the capsule that kept Yurisha alive while she was in a coma.
ユリーシャの生命機能を維持した
あのカプセルなら　可能だ))
（ハーモニカの演奏）
Captain...
（徳川）艦長…　艦長！
Captain!
（沖田十三）んん…。　ん？
（徳川）大丈夫ですか？
うなされておりましたぞ。
Are you all right? You were having a nightmare.
I was dreaming... About Mamoru Kodai.
夢を見たよ。　古代守の夢だった。
あっ　そういえば　彼は　キリシマで
わしらと一緒でしたな。
Come to think of it, he was with us on the Kirishima.
You were the captain, and I ran the engines.
あんたが艦長で　わしが機関長。→
And he was a new Weapons Officer, yes?
あいつは　新米の砲雷長か。
第二次火星沖海戦→
You're talking about the Second Battle of Mars?
あのときの話かね？
The one battle we won.
わしらが勝った唯一の戦いでした。
あれのおかげで
なんとか　ガミラスの侵攻を→
That success allowed us to push back the Garmillas invasion.
後らせられましたからな。
But much was lost there, as well.
だが　失うものも大きかった。
徳川君。
はい。
Tokugawa...
Yes?
この艦は　いい艦だ。
そう思わんか？
Don't you think this is a good ship?
It is.
ああ…　いい艦です。
わしは　この艦を誇りに思う。
I'm proud of this ship.
The flames of my life will not endure much longer.
わしの　この命の炎も→
間もなく消えるだろう。
あっ…。
だが　この艦は死なん。
But this ship will live on. I want to pass this soul to the younger generation.
この魂は　若いヤツらに託したい。
何を縁起でもない。
Why so gloomy all of a sudden?
I won't die yet. Not until I've seen Earth with my own eyes.
わしは　まだ死なんよ→
この目で　地球を見るまではな。
ははっ…。
I'll get going, then.
（徳川）では　行きますか。→
Yamazaki is talented, but I still haven't taught him all we must impart.
山崎は優秀だが
まだ　わしらの生きざまは→
伝えきっておりません。
そういえば　古代守も→
By the way, wasn't Mamoru Kodai meant to be on the Yamato?
本当は　ヤマトに…。
弟が　立派に受け継いでいる。
His younger brother is doing his job just fine.
Nanbu. Nanbu.
（ＡＵ０９）南部サン　南部サン。
（南部）あっ？
（ＡＵ０９）相原サン→
What's wrong with Aihara?
ドウシタノデスカ？
この前の　地球との交信だよ。
That last communication with Earth...
Yes?
ハイ？
（南部）つらい真実ってやつ。
It's a hard truth to accept.
（相原）父さんが死んで→
My father's dead... And my aging mother is alone at home.
家には　年老いた母さん一人。→
They say that Earth's a mess!
地球は　ひどい状況だって
いうじゃないですか。→
At this rate, my mother won't last much longer, either...
このままじゃ
いずれ　母さんだって…。
It's true that Earth is nearly dead.
確かに　地球は瀕死の状況だ。
But crying won't save it.
だが
泣き言を言っても地球は救えない。
The Yamato will make it! We'll make it in time!
ヤマトは間に合う！
手遅れなんかにしない。
俺たちが　間に合わせるんだ！
We'll ensure it does!
He's kind of acting like the Captain.
（百合亜）
なんか　艦長みたいですね。
Leave it to me! I've got the helm!
（太田）任せてくださいよ！
この俺が　舵を取ってるんですよ。
予定よりも　早く地球に…。
≫シューン（ドアの音）
I'll get us to Earth ahead of schedule.
≫（島）誰が舵を取ってるんだって？
（太田・百合亜）えっ？
Who's got the helm?
Time for shift change.
（島）交代の時間だ。
I've been waiting for you!
（太田）お待ちしておりました！
（島）副長は？
Where's the XO?
（百合亜）
コスモリバースの調整で→
He went to the Wave Motion Gun Control Room to adjust the Cosmo Reverser.
波動砲制御室に行かれました。
（島）そうか。
I see.
島！
あっ…　ん？→
Shima...
古代。
これ　お前にも。
Kodai?
This one's for you.
こいつは…。→
Look at this.
An Invitation to Kato and Harada's Wedding Party
It finally happened, huh?
いよいよ　年貢の納めどきか。
It wasn't easy persuading Kato. He's so old-fashioned.
嫌がる加藤を説得するのに
苦労したよ。
あいつは　古風だからな。
まあ　なんにしても→
Anyway, it's nice to have something cheery going on.
めでたいのは　いいことさ。
（加藤）いいのかな？
≪（真琴）ん？　似合ってなかった？
Is this really okay?
It didn't look good on me?
いや…
俺たちだけ　こんなふうでさ。
No, I mean... Our being the only ones that have something like this.
You mean Kodai?
（真琴）古代さんのこと？
あいつ　無理して
明るく振る舞ってやがる。→
He's forcing himself to act cheerful.
ほんとは
自分が　どん底のくせに…。
But in reality, he's falling apart.
It doesn't matter! Let's do this!
いいじゃない！　やろうよ！
（加藤）あっ…。
We must share our happiness with him!
（真琴）
私たちが　元気を分けてあげるの！
（加藤）真琴…。
（真琴）この子だって→
Makoto...
I'm sure our child says the same thing.
きっと　そう言ってるよ。
ふっ…　そうだな。
You're right.
So decide which one is best.
（真琴）
だから　どれがいいか決めて。
Traditional Japanese kimonos, then.
（加藤）じゃあ　文金高島田で。
（真琴）却下！
No!
New life is born as the old passes away, huh?
（佐渡）生まれてくるものもあれば
死んでいくものもある…　か。
誰ノ　オ話デスカ？
Who are you talking about?
I don't know.
（佐渡）さあな。→
しかし　イスカンダルからこっち
よう来るのう　お前は。
Anyway, since we left Iscandar, you've been coming here frequently.
I suppose this place calms me.
ココガ　落チ着クカラデショウ。
ぷはぁ～…　そうか。
I see... Then stay here forever.
じゃあ
いつまでも　ここにおればええ。
Huh?
ハテナ？
Stay here!
おればええんじゃよ！
ピッピッピッピッ…（キーボード操作音）
Yuki, Kato and I are getting married soon.
（真琴）雪さん　今度　私
加藤さんと一緒になるんです。→
そしたらね…　聞いてくださいよ→
And then, get this...
古代さんがね　「パーティーをしろ！
するべきだ！」って→
Kodai says, "Have a party! You have to!"
That's what he told Kato. And Kato was mortified, but ended up agreeing.
彼に言ったらしいんですよ。→
それで　本当は
恥ずかしくて　やりたくないのに→
無理しちゃって…。→
Guys are so cute, aren't they?
男って　ほんと　かわいいですよね。
あっ　あぁ…　雪さん！
Yuki!
Finally... Just wait! I'll get the doctor!
やった…。　待っててください！→
すぐ　先生呼びますからね！
ピッ（操作音）
Doctor! Get over here!
（真琴）先生　すぐ来てください！
Where? To automatic navigation!
どこって　自動航法室に決まって…。
（森雪）あっ…　あぁ…。
（真田）君は　どう見る？
What do you think?
It's an interlocking recursive structure.
（新見）
再帰的で　複雑な連結構造。→
まるで
脳のニューラルネットワークのようですね。
Like a brain's neural network.
The Cosmo Reverse System is like a living creature.
（真田）
このコスモリバースシステムは→
いわば
一個の生命体のようなものだ。→
It's possible.
ない話ではない。
Then this wave motion pattern is the memory required to rebuild Earth?
じゃあ　この波動パターンが→
地球再生に　必要な記憶？
（真田）問題は→
The question is to whom that memory belongs.
その記憶が　一体
誰のものなのかということだ。
You don't think it's the memories of all the Yamato's crew?
（桐生）それは　我々ヤマト乗組員→
全員の記憶なんじゃないですか？
それ以外は…。
I can't think of anything else.
But is that really it?
（真田）果たして　そうだろうか？
（桐生）えっ？
Could it be...
（心の声）≪やはり　お前なのか…≫
You?
≪ピッピー　ピッピー（受信音）
んん…。
Yes, this is the Wave Motion Control Room.
（佐野）
はい　こちら　波動砲制御室。→
Don't yell at me like that!
ううっ！　そんな　いきなり
どならないでください！→
Yes, the XO is here.
はい。
副長なら　いらっしゃいます。→
But what happened to Officer Mori, Doctor Sado?
だから　森船務長が
どうされたんですか？　佐渡先生。
[TEL]
Yes.
はい…。
ピィーー（心電計の音）
はぁ　はぁ　はぁ　はぁ…。
No...
そんな…。
（真琴）うぅ　ううっ…。
うぅ…　くっ！
うわぁ～～～!!
ああっ！　はぁ　はぁ　はぁ…。
（佐渡）亡くなる直前→
Before she died, she miraculously opened her eyes.
奇跡的に　目を覚ましたらしい。
The last thing she said was your name.
最後に
お前の名前を　呼んでいたそうだ。
（真琴）「あなたに会いたい」って…。
She said she wanted to see you again.
僕もだ…。　僕も君に→
Me, too...
I wanted to see you again, too.
もう一度　会いたかった…。
真田さん　お願いがあります。
XO Sanada, I have a request.
Don't tell anyone about this.
このことは
みんなに伏せておいてください。
（２人）えっ…。
（真琴）えっ？
やっと　地球に帰れるんだ。
At last, we're almost home.
I don't want them to hear any more sad news.
もう　これ以上→
あいつらに
悲しい知らせを聞かせたくない。
（拍手）
Congratulations on your marriage!
（ざわめき）
（篠原）
ははっ。　今度は　俺たちの番か…。
So it's our turn now, huh?
（玲）ふん！
なっ!?　ぐはっ…。
おめでとう。
（加藤）お…　おう。
Congratulations.
原田君も。
（真琴）ありがとうございます。
And to you, Harada.
Thank you.
（加藤）古代
ヤマトに配属になったときのこと→
Kodai, do you remember when we were assigned to the Yamato?
覚えてるか？
ん？
俺は　あのとき
お前に　こう言った。
Back then, I said this to you...
「貴様の命令で　部下が
犬死にするようなことがあったら→
That if your orders caused one of my men to die needlessly, I'd never forgive you.
許さない」ってな。　だが→
So...
You've done better than I could have hoped.
お前は
これまで立派にやってきた。→
誰よりも立派にだ。
それは　俺が保証する。→
Better than anyone.
I guarantee that.
だから　森君も大丈夫だ！
（真琴）はっ…　サブちゃん！
So Mori will be fine!
Sabu!
（加藤）えっ？　な…　なんだよ？
Wh-What?
Kato...
加藤。
（２人）あっ。
Make her happy.
彼女を幸せにしろよ。
Mamoru Kodai?
（新見）
古代守!?　システムの中核が→
The system core is Kodai?
あの古代君だっていうんですか!?
（真田）論理的に考えた末
導き出した答えだ。
After following the chain of logic, that is my answer.
Doctor...
先生…　艦内で→
Have you heard the rumors about a ghost on the ship?
幽霊を目撃したって話があるの→
ご存じですか？
（真田）ん？
You might laugh at me for being unscientific,
非科学的と
笑われるかもしれませんが→
but I saw it, as well. It was Kodai!
私も見たんです。　あれは確かに→
古代君でした！
"Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic," huh?
十分に発達した科学技術は→
魔法と見分けがつかない…　か。
（新見）えっ？
おそらく　イスカンダルで
息を引き取ったあと→
After he died on Iscandar,
Chuya Nakahara Poems
his memories were probably saved in some form.
なんらかの方法で
その記憶だけは→
保存されていたのだろう。
（乗組員）もうすぐ
地球が　間近に見えるらしいぞ！
We're almost close enough to see Earth up close!
Let's all go see it!
（乗組員）
みんなで　地球を見に行こうぜ！
And his consciousness is the core to activate the Cosmo Reverse System.
（真田）そして　その意識は
コスモリバースシステムを→
起動させる核となった。→
Right now, Mamoru Kodai himself is the Cosmo Reverse System.
今や　古代守が
コスモリバースシステムそのもの。→
No, he is the Yamato itself.
いや…　ヤマトそのものなのだ。
≫カン　カン（足音）
雪…
君と　初めて出会ったときのこと→
Yuki...
Do you remember
the first time we met?
覚えているかい？
Back then, I was so angry about my brother...
あのとき　僕は　兄さんのことで
頭に　血が上っていて→
出会いとしては
いいとは言えなかったね。
It wasn't the best way to meet someone.
それから　ヤマトに
一緒に乗ることになって→
After that, we both came aboard the Yamato...
考え方の違いから
よくケンカもして。
Our different ways of thinking meant we fought all the time.
そうするうちに　僕に→
But eventually,
you told me how you'd lost your memories.
記憶をなくした話を
してくれたっけ。
And about how you kept trying to stay positive...
それでも　前向きに生きてる君に→
僕は
自分でも気が付かないうちに→
Without even knowing it,
I found myself drawn to you.
どんどん惹かれていったんだ。
君が　さらわれたとき→
When you were kidnapped,
and when we met again...
そして　再び出会ったあのとき→
僕は　自分の本当の気持ちに
気が付いた。
I realized how I really felt.
I love you.
君が好きだ。
この世界の誰よりも　君が！
I love you more than anyone in the world.
Is there even any point
君のいない地球に…→
to a world without you?
君のいない地球なんかに
意味があるのか？
意味が！　ううっ…　あぁ…。
Is there?
Susumu, this is all I can do for you.
（守）進　俺がお前にしてやれるのは
これくらいだ。
艦を　お返しします　沖田さん。
I return your ship to you,
Captain Okita.
Cosmo Reverse System Activated
システムが　勝手に作動している!?
（桐生）そんな…　どうして!?
The system is starting up on its own!
No... Why?
（佐野）分からないよ！
（２人）ううっ！　あっ…。
I don't know!
（桐生）出力　急速低下！
（佐野）まずい　このままでは…。
Output is dropping fast!
Oh, no! At this rate...
（真田）現状維持しろ！
コスモリバースを停止させるな。
Keep things steady! Don't shut down the Cosmo Reverser.
（佐野）ダメです！　こちらの
アクセスを受け付けません。
It's no good! It won't accept our commands.
（新見）くっ！
（佐野）うわっ…。
そんな…　先生！
No... Doctor!
（真田）なぜだ…。
あっ。
Why?
Chuya Nakahara Poems
Why, Kodai?
（真田）なぜだ!?　古代！→
なぜ　今　動かしたんだ!?
Why did you start it now?
これは…。
What is this?
あっ…　ああっ！
古代…　君？
Kodai?
Yuki!
雪…。
ううっ…　あぁ…。
雪！
Yuki!
私　どうして…。
Why am I...
あのとき　撃たれて→
I was shot, and then...
それから…。
夢だよ。
夢？
It was a dream.
A dream?
それは　夢だ。
It was a dream. You were having a bad dream.
君は　悪い夢を見ていたんだ。
古代君。
Kodai!
Inspect every part of the Cosmo Reverser! Prepare to reboot!
（真田）各部点検　急がせろ！
再起動準備だ！
（新見）
彼の意識でもある起動パルスは→
The activation pulse that was his mind...
ほとんど　量子の海に消失して→
It's almost entirely lost in the quantum sea.
It cannot be reactivated.
再起動できません…。
（佐野）えっ!?
それじゃあ　ヤマトが戻っても…。
Then, even if the Yamato returns...
（桐生）
地球を救うことは…　できない？
We won't be able to save Earth?
Kodai... No, Yamato!
（真田）古代…　いや　ヤマト！
（３人）ん？
Is this your will? Is this what you wanted?
これが　お前の意思か!?
お前が望んだことだというのか!?
（南部）地球だ…　地球が見えるぞ！
Earth! We can see Earth!
Doctor Sado...
佐渡先生。
はっ？
Would you leave me alone for a moment?
わしを　しばらく
一人にしてはくれまいか？
Doctor Sado...
佐渡先生。
あっ…。
ありがとう。
Thank you.
≪ガチャ　バタン（ドアの音）
Earth, huh?
≪地球か…≫
≪何もかも　皆　懐かしい≫
Everything brings back so many memories...
Rebooting
The Cosmo Reverse System has reactivated. What happened?
（新見）コスモリバースシステム→
再起動を確認…。　一体　何が!?
分からない。　ただ→
I don't know, but...
奇跡というものが　起きただけだ。
A miracle has occurred.
≪守…≫
Mamoru!
Goodbye, Sanada.
（守）さよなら　真田。→
さよなら　薫。
Goodbye, Kaoru.
ん？　えっ！　ええ～!?
≪ん？
≫あっ！
≫おい…。
≪えっ!?
（どよめき）
（島）あるんだな…　こういうの。
I guess stuff like this does happen.
（百合亜）おかえりなさ～い！
ううっ…　うぅ…。
Welcome back!
ただいま。
（島）おかえり。→
I'm back.
Welcome back.
よく帰って来たね。
Welcome home.
（南部）森君！　えっ？
Mori!
（玲）森船務長の帰還を…。
（２人）あっ。
We all welcome Officer Mori's return.
（玲）一同　歓迎します。
（百合亜）あっ…　ああっ！
ふふっ。　ありがと。
Thank you.
ん!?
あっ　あぁ…。
December 8th, 2199
Space Battleship Yamato returns to Earth.
カンボジアの首都プノンペンの中
心部で２８日、
日本人の女性観光客が
２人組の男にカバンを奪われそう
になり、
抵抗した際に銃で足を撃たれてケ
ガをした。